上一次我們提過出埃及這件事
是在公元前1500至1200年間發生
當時的世界都是面臨史無前例的動盪
近東有很多人正在遷徙移居
想找一個安居之所
我們舉個例子就是海人Sea People
其中一組人就是菲利士人Philistines
在大歷史圖畫中以色列人是其中一群在遷徙
他們在埃及被欺壓多年
離開時前無去路後有追兵
但有特別的地方是他們發現上帝親自帶領他們
對於今天你和我面對社會政局的不穩
有一種被迫的感覺流散在世界不同的地方
同樣面對很多改變身份改變和未知之數
這樣看出埃及這個故事對我們來說是非常切身
但當我們看出埃及這個技術時
我們一定要梳理一下歷史的問題
為什麼呢?因為在舊約聖經中
經常提到出埃及這件歷史事蹟
可以這樣說在舊約歷史中出埃及這件事
就有如新約的耶穌基督從死裡復活
歷史性都是這麼重要
但在過去幾十年越來越多人質疑
為什麼沒有證據證明出埃及這件事
或者可能出埃及是很後期虛構的故事
我記得好幾年前在香港電台上受過訪問
主持人問了一個問題很有道理
他說出埃及這麼大件事總會有少少線索
居然一點線索都沒有
有些道理我們必須承認
暫時到現在都沒有直接的歷史證明
但我們這樣說也好
我們都需要留意幾點
第一就是證據的不存在
不一定等於不存在的證據
這個你動高床板就要想一想
The absence of evidence is not the evidence of absence
因為很多歷史事跡
包括聖經或聖經以外的歷史事跡
都未必找到考古的證據
我們不能夠踏時光機回去以前
將歷史放在化驗室裡面去證明多一次
何況當時的背景
埃及帝國是獨裁的政權
他們不會將失敗的事跡寫下
第二件事我們需要留意
當我們想起考古證據的時候
我們對考古證據的要求一定要實際
假設以色列人出埃及的話
你想一下他們會帶著什麼
他們好像難民一樣離開埃及
我不知道你有沒有做過服務難民的工作
我記得有一次我參與一個難民服務的工作
去到機場接一家六口從剛果難民營來的難民
六個人他們入境下機的時候
每個人你想一下他們帶著什麼
他們只是帶著一個小的膠袋
就是這麼多
所以你再想一想
作為難民甚至作為平民百姓也好
過了一百年之後
你看我們這班平民百姓的人
都一定是蕭聲匿跡的
就是說在考古歷史裡面是看不到我們的
所以為什麼有這麼多皇帝想建皇陵
大墳墓有兵馬俑金字塔等等
因為他們想留芳百世
所以沒有考古證據不代表你不存在
再有一點需要留意
如果你真的按照聖經所說
以色列人在埃及裡面住了好幾代
如果他們出埃及的時候
你想一下他們帶著什麼實物出來
衣服、瓷器、日用品等等
但這些全部的東西
都必定是埃及製造的
是在埃及製造的
所以他們到曠野就算留下這些實物
我們找到的
我們只會當有一班埃及人
他們經過留下過
舉個很簡單的例子
我的子女都是在美國出生長大的
我看遍他們擁有的實物
我找不到哪一樣可以直接表明他們是華裔第二代
除了他們現在在生的樣子
像亞裔的人
但他們說話、吃東西、想的東西
都是美國本土化的
所以我想如果他們真的化了灰的話
他們的實物跟其他白人、黑人
這裡的美國人是沒有任何分別的
所以我們對考古證據的要求
是需要實際一點的
我們不會找到一塊石頭
上面寫著摩西到此一遊
你說沒有直接的歷史考古證據
是不是就這樣算了
其實也不是的
在歷史的探索裡面
我們再問一個問題
有沒有間接性的、情況性的、背景的旁證
即是circumstantial background的evidence
如果這樣問的話
可能真的有
因為如果出埃及記
真的是後期虛構著作
即是到波斯時代、公元前500年的時候才寫
他的描述裡面一定會用一些後期的字眼
但是如果出埃及記
真的寫當時的歷史事跡
他的描述一定是配合當時的語言
當時的環境
如果是這樣的話
歷史可靠性就會高很多
你問前前後後
又說早期又後期的描述
好像很難明白、很抽象
其實一點都不難明白
我播一下一個短片
你就知道有什麼問題
是,駱Sir
失憶的大軍要二十天才到達白里浦
但每日的軍餉二十萬兩
我們的國庫已經所剩無幾
浸暫時不能給太多
為今之計
只要交了十五、十六和十七這三天的軍餉
其他的就慢慢想辦法
駱Sir,讓盧平替你換一盆熱水
周兄長,跟浸再檢查一下
看各地各省還有沒有人欠稅
浸要把水行一次過追回來
實不相似
明眼人一看就明白
因為浸是不會用check這個字
看起來好像很好笑
但其實這裡點出了一樣東西
就是如何鑒定一個歷史文件可靠性的原則
古話說出埃及記
如果歷史可靠的話
它裡面的描述一定是吻合公元前1500至1000年之間
那時是New Kingdom Period
是古埃及帝國的新王國時期
那時是埃及最後輝煌的時期
看當時埃及的歷史文件
用什麼字眼
描述什麼地理
然後再比對一下
出埃及記我們就知道歷史的可靠性
舉幾個例子
出埃及記一章第十一節
於是埃及人派督公管轄他們
即是以色列人
加重他們的負擔和害他們
他們為法老建造兩座積火城
就是彼東和蘭室
使他們因做苦工覺得命苦
無論和禮 造磚 做田間各樣的工
在一切的工上都嚴嚴待他們
這裡細緻的描述
造磚 和禮和一切的工
我帶你去一個埃及的墓穴
叫做Tomb of Rekhmire
雷克米爾墓穴
這個人是公元前15世紀
即是1400多年的時候
在埃及做大官
在他的墓穴有很多壁畫
裡面描述很多奴隸
包括戰俘
他們在田間做很多事
這個跟出埃及記的描述非常吻合
你看到圖畫這一部分
有人在池裡取水
有些奴隸在和禮
有些在造磚
包括田間各樣的工作
細緻地看的時候
埃及的督工是拿著木棒來管轄他們
另一方面我們可以看地理
一章第十一節
兩座積火城
叫彼東和蘭室
蘭室是法老的名字
有一個很出名的法老王
叫蘭室二世 或蘭室大帝
Ramesses II
蘭室城真的存在
Ramesses 或 Ramesses
在舊約聖經裡只提過五次
都是在摩西五經裡提過
而我們知道蘭室城
Pyramuses 城市
在埃及的文獻裡出現過
也是蘭室二世的法老所建的京都
說起蘭室二世的法老
他就很有名
因為很多人都認為
這個很可能是出埃及的法老
但說到考古
蘭室城我們知道的
只有二百年的歷史
由公元前1270至1070年之間
為什麼最後會被荒廢呢
因為當時利羅河在三角洲平地經常改道
利羅河對埃及人來說
是很重要的
等於今天的高速公路
交通 貿易 軍事的輸流都是靠利羅河
所以利羅河改道
城市在兩百年之後就被荒廢
埃及人很會復原
他們就把本身在蘭室城的石碑
有蘭室二世的名字的石碑
搬到北面十二英里
建另外一個城鎮
那個城鎮叫索安
Zoan 或希臘文是丹尼斯
說起索安城或丹尼斯
如果你記得或接觸過
1981年有一套電影叫《奪寶奇兵》
In the End of Jones' Waders of the Lost Ark
裡面提及過丹尼斯的古城
電影裡的橋段是二次大戰時
德國納粹黨要法國考古學家
去丹尼斯索安找藥櫃
你看看以下短短兩三分鐘的片段
你告訴我有什麼真有虛構
Dr. Jones, I've heard a great deal about you.
Have you?
Professor of Archaeology,
Expert on the occult,
and I just want to say it,
obtainer of rare antiquities.
One way of saying it,
why don't you sit down,
you'll be more comfortable.
Thank you.
Yes, you're a man of many talents.
You studied under Professor Ravenwood
at the University of Chicago.
Yes, I did.
Dr. Jones, you must understand
that this is all strictly confidential.
I understand.
Yesterday afternoon,
our European sections intercepted
a German communique
that was sent from Cairo to Berlin.
You see, over the last two years,
the Nazis have had teams of archaeologists
running around the world
looking for all kinds of religious artifacts.
Hitler's a nut on the subject.
He's crazy.
He's obsessed with the occult.
And right now,
apparently there's some kind of
German archaeological dig
going on in the desert
outside of Cairo.
We've got some information here,
but we can't make anything out of it,
and maybe you can.
Tannis Development Proceeding
Acquire Headpiece
Staff of Ra
Abner Ravenwood, U.S.
Nazis have discovered Tannis.
What does that mean to you, Tannis?
Well, the city of Tannis
is one of the possible resting places
of the Lost Ark.
The Lost Ark?
Yes, the Ark of the Covenant,
the chest the Hebrews used to carry
around the Ten Commandments.
What do you mean, Ten Commandments?
You're talking about the Ten Commandments?
Yes, the actual Ten Commandments,
the original stone tablets
that Moses brought down out of Mount Harab
and smashed, if you believe in that sort of thing.
Did you guys ever go to Sunday school?
Well, I...
No, look.
The Hebrews took the broken pieces
and put them in the Ark.
When they settled in Canaan,
they put the Ark in a place
called the Temple of Solomon in Jerusalem,
where it stayed for many years
until all of a sudden, whoosh, it's gone.
Where?
Well, nobody knows where or when.
However, an Egyptian pharaoh...
Sisak.
Yes, invaded the city of Jerusalem
around about 980 B.C.,
and he may have taken the Ark
back to the city of Tannis
and hidden it in a secret chamber
called the Well of Souls.
Secret chamber?
However, about a year after
the pharaoh had returned to Egypt,
the city of Tannis was consumed by the desert
in a sandstorm which lasted a whole year,
wiped clean by the wrath of God.
What does this Ark look like?
I don't know.
There's a picture of it right here.
That's it.
Good God.
Yes, that's just what the Hebrews thought.
What's that supposed to be coming out of there?
Lightning, fire, power of God or something.
You don't understand Hitler's interest in it.
Oh, yes.
The Bible speaks of the Ark leveling mountains
and laying waste to entire regions.
An army which carries the Ark before it
is invincible.
What is the truth?
If you've been to Sunday School,
you'll know that there's a Ark.
And you'll know that
900 years before the Temple was built,
there was a pharaoh named Shishak.
He really attacked Jerusalem
and took away the treasures
from the Temple and the palace.
This is what the 14th chapter of the Book of Kings
has told us.
The Ark's whereabouts
is another big topic.
We won't talk about it today.
But anyway,
when it comes to Tennis,
Denis, Soin, Zouan,
these cities,
it's true that since 1928,
the French archaeologists
have been excavating.
They've been doing it for years.
In the early years,
the French archaeologists
thought that Soin, Zouan, and Tennis
were the epicenter of the Egyptian War.
They found the remains of the dead
and the stone tablets.
But now they know that it's not true.
Soin and Tennis
are an ancient city of 1,000 years.
But they were built in 1070.
So it's a post-historical city.
The later books of the Bible
also mention Soin and Tennis.
In the 12th chapter of the 78th chapter of the Book of Psalms,
it says that God was in Soin,
the fields of Soin,
the fields of Tennis,
and was doing a miracle
in front of the Pharaoh.
This is very important.
The 78th chapter of the Book of Psalms
is about the plague in Egypt.
But it says that the place where the plague happened
was Soin, not Nanset.
So when the poet wrote this poem,
he recalled the plague.
He wrote it after 4,500 years
after the plague.
At that time, Nanset had already ceased to exist.
So the poet only knew
that the plague had happened
in the city of Soin near Nanset.
But when you go back to the time of the plague,
you see the details of the geography
mentioning Nanset.
This town really existed at that time.
So when it was recorded,
the reliability of history was shown.
You may think it is very complicated.
But it is not complicated at all.
It is also very simple.
For example,I have lived in Chicago for 20 years.
I only know the geographical location and geography
of Chicago in the past 20 years.
You can ask some old Chinese here.
They can tell you that
40 or 50 years ago,
the name of the restaurant in the same place
was "Meng".
Today we have really determined
the location of Nanset.
It is a small village in Alibaba
called Cantia.
Here we find the stone wall of Nanset.
It also has its royal name.
There are Nanset's great soldiers on the stone wall.
They are attacking its enemies.
It is said that the Bible often mentions
the new-made shield of the great man.
It is the political idiom
that the French used at that time.
In Nanset,we also find
the military horse-drawn carriage.
There are also many large stones for horse-drawn carriages.
It is estimated that the horse-drawn carriage
can stop 500 horses
and more than 200 chariots.
Nanset is estimated to be
as large as 10 square kilometers.
Now it is a field.
But it was the largest city in the world at that time.
The Egyptian Bible also contains
many special idioms and words
that the Egyptians used at that time.
But there is no word for the Persian period.
On the contrary,the books written later
such as the Book of Ezekiel and the Book of Nehemiah
often contain Persian words.
We have just spent about 15 minutes
to talk about the historical reality
of the Egyptian Bible.
We don't need to doubt it.
Now we can see
the Egyptian route of the Israelites.
How did God lead the Israelites to Egypt?
They set out from Nanset.
In the 13th chapter of chapter 17,
it is mentioned that when Pharaoh went there with his people,
the roads to Philistine were narrow.
God did not lead them where to go.
Because God said,
"I am afraid that when the people see the battle,
they will regret it and turn back to Egypt."
So God led the people to go astray
and went the way of the Red Sea.
Here is a road called the road to Philistine.
This road was also mentioned
in the Egyptian documents at that time.
The other name of Egypt is
the Way of Horus.
It is the way of Horus, the Egyptian god.
The way to Philistine was the most convenient way.
It took a few days to reach the land of Philistine.
But the Bible says
God did not lead the Israelites to the fastest way.
Why?
Because God said,
"I am afraid that when the people see the battle,
they will regret it and turn back to Egypt."
This is a good example.
On the road to the northwest of the Mediterranean,
we found a lot of soldiers from the New Kingdom.
More than ten soldiers.
There were Egyptian war horses on this road
to guard the land.
It was a military stronghold.
So the Bible tells us
that if the Israelites took this shortest way,
they would not have been well equipped
and would not have fought well.
They would have regretted it and turned back to Egypt.
The way God led people to go
was not necessarily the shortest and fastest.
It was not necessarily our plan.
Sometimes it was not even in line with the law.
The other way to Egypt
was the way to the shore in the Bible.
This is what we saw in Genesis.
Do you remember the story?
When Haggai went out,
he walked on the way to the shore.
So the Israelites started from Lancester
and walked to the southeast.
According to the Bible,
they should have gone out of Egypt through the Shu'i Basin
and then went to Galilee.
But what did the 14th chapter say?
It said, "And suddenly there was a great storm.
And God commanded the Israelites to turn back."
It means to go north.
They went to the sea of ​​red.
It was actually in front of the sea of ​​grass.
The Israelites were afraid of the storm.
So they turned back to Egypt.
So they walked on the way to the south.
God suddenly called them to turn back.
Why?
When they were about to go out,
God called them to turn back.
What was God's will?
In the 14th chapter, verse 3,
God said, "And Pharaoh said,
'The Israelites were lost on the ground,
and the wilderness had trapped them.'
In the 14th chapter,
God said, "I will make Pharaoh's heart strong,
and he will chase them.
And then I will be glorified
in Pharaoh and his whole army."
The Egyptians knew that they were in the wilderness.
So the Israelites walked on.
God's command seems to be very complicated.
It's not humanly reasonable.
But what is the ultimate goal?
It is to be glorified to God.
God's purpose is not to make us feel sad and empty.
It's not that people think
they are doing well and that's it.
God's command is needed
to make us learn to trust Him.
At the beginning, we said that
there are many changes in life.
Especially in the pandemic,
we have encountered many unideal situations.
We all want to go to an ideal place.
We always say that we don't like this situation,
don't like this place,
don't like this context.
So we want to walk away.
We think that's OK.
Of course, this is humanly reasonable.
But this story seems to tell us
what is the most important thing in God's eyes.
The most important thing is not what we think.
Everything is fine and good.
In chapter 14, verse 30,
it says, "On that day, Jehovah saved the Israelites
and took the hands of the Egyptians."
It says that they crossed the Red Sea.
What did the Israelites see?
They saw Jehovah's victory.
They saw Jehovah's great deeds to the Egyptians.
They knew how to glorify Him,
how to trust God and His divine power.
When we encounter difficulties,
we think that we are leaving this unideal situation.
We are looking for an ideal place.
If God really wants to lead us to our ultimate goal,
without disasters, without worries, without sickness,
we can retire and live happily,
I think God is the most unsuccessful prophet.
The most successful one should be Jehovah.
Because in the Egyptian Empire,
if you put your trust in Him, you can live in peace.
So, you see, when the Israelites left Egypt,
they were not able to enjoy their eternal peace.
In fact, after the Israelites left Egypt,
they crossed the Red Sea and the Sea of ​​Grass.
It was a trial.
Because God's purpose was to prepare us
to become a group of people who were faithful to His will.
This is the greatest blessing.
The greatest blessing is not that we have no disasters, no sickness,
no epidemic.
The greatest blessing is that we can become the children of God,
and be with Him.
We can be so glorious
that we can become people who serve God.
We are now facing different disasters.
Whether it is an epidemic or a downturn in life,
we may need to ask
whether we will still be loyal to God
after these disasters and downturns.
We just need to be there to answer the call.
We have not learned to be more faithful to God.
Or when we have passed the command of God,
we will be more faithful to God.
Personally, the same is true for the Church.
God said, "Do not waste the path He has led us on."
No matter what the disaster is,
let us, the Church,
be able to experience new lessons.
Let us, the Church,
become a Church that is more in line with His will.
Some scholars said it was very interesting.
They said, "The main thing that God wants to do in the Exodus
is to take Israelite out of Egypt."
God did not want to take the Israelites out of Egypt.
After they left Egypt,
they still had a heart for Egypt.
They wanted to return to the Egyptian Empire
because there was a stable and prosperous place.
God wanted to take Egypt out of the Israelites
and take the Pharaoh out of Egypt
and take away the idols
like Moses,
who was a prosperous man
and a man of peace.
So that we can truly return to God
and be faithful to Him
and serve Him,
Are we willing to do that?
Let God take away these idols
and let our hearts truly return to Him.
Let us pray with our hearts.
God, we know that Your way
and Your great command
is not what we humans think.
Your ultimate goal
is to make our lives belong to You.
God, we pray that You take away
the things we long for in our lives
like stability and prosperity
and the benefits that the land can give us.
God, let our lives truly belong to You.
Let You be our true Lord.
You continue to lead our lives
and the path ahead of us.
No matter what we are going through,
let us know that the ultimate goal
is not only to be free and carefree
but to be faithful to You.
Continue to train us,
continue to help us,
and nurture us
so that we can become
more fit for Your will.
Let us pray.
God bless you.
《神的道路》
作詞:李宗盛 作曲:李宗盛
神的道路
高過人的路
神的一念
高過人的一念
他的心裡有藍圖
他的世界不作物
一步一步帶領的前途
他離大地的更近
他讓雲在空中漂浮
是他創造生命氣息
是他隱世照顧自負
神走萬物和愛棲息
愛心等待你要歡呼
啊 愛心等待要歡呼
神的道路
高過人的路
神的一念
高過人的一念
他的心裡有藍圖
他的世界不作物
一步一步帶領的前途
他離大地的更近
他讓雲在空中漂浮
是他創造生命氣息
是他隱世照顧自負
神走萬物和愛棲息
愛心等待你要歡呼
啊 愛心等待要歡呼
啊 他離大地的更近
他讓雲在空中漂浮
是他創造生命氣息
是他隱世照顧自負
神走萬物和愛棲息
愛心等待你要歡呼
啊 愛心等待要歡呼
啊 要歡呼
由 Amara.org 社群提供的字幕
「愛心等待要歡呼」
(字幕由 Amara.org 社群提供)